<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-16T11:25:12+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Vibrotactile materials in artistic performance</title><subtitle>Exploring feedback and resonances in various materials, by using audio feedback techniques as the exploratory device. Utilizing these methods to create new instruments for artistic performance. The mthods also give us the opportunity to reflect upon the differences between a scientific measurement and and artistic exploration (of these materials, but supposedly the poerspective might be transferrable to other domains of study). The github site is the project bog, and might also hold sources of software made for the project.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Demovideo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/16/demovideo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Demovideo" /><published>2020-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/16/demovideo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/16/demovideo.html">&lt;p&gt;A short demo video made in the office. A 30x30cm polycarbonate plate, transducer mounted somewhat offcenter. Piezo microphone attached to finger. The sound of the microphone is routed back to the transducer, and the feedback circuit is closed when the finger touches the plate. The plate has many vibrational modes, each of which has a resonance potential at a specific frequency. By moving the finger to different positions on the plate, different vibrational modes can be activated, and the mode frequency contributes to the resonance of the feedback loop. By touching the plate with a second finger (other than the one with the microphone attached), I can dampen selected vibrational modes, and thus suppress feedback on that frequency. This allows other resonance potentials to rise and become the most prominent, thereby changing the pitch of the sound we hear. In certain conditions, several vibrational modes can become approximately equal in strength, and then we will hear several frequencies at the same time. Some of the vibration modes are very closely spaced. This means that very movements of the fingers can affect the sound significantly. The instrument is this very sensitive to expressional variations in performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video recorded 15. October 2020. Performer: Øyvind Brandtsegg.
&lt;a href=&quot;../../../media/materials_feed_demo_2020_10_14.webm&quot; title=&quot;Link Title&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/materials_demo_video_still.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alternate Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A short demo video made in the office. A 30x30cm polycarbonate plate, transducer mounted somewhat offcenter. Piezo microphone attached to finger. The sound of the microphone is routed back to the transducer, and the feedback circuit is closed when the finger touches the plate. The plate has many vibrational modes, each of which has a resonance potential at a specific frequency. By moving the finger to different positions on the plate, different vibrational modes can be activated, and the mode frequency contributes to the resonance of the feedback loop. By touching the plate with a second finger (other than the one with the microphone attached), I can dampen selected vibrational modes, and thus suppress feedback on that frequency. This allows other resonance potentials to rise and become the most prominent, thereby changing the pitch of the sound we hear. In certain conditions, several vibrational modes can become approximately equal in strength, and then we will hear several frequencies at the same time. Some of the vibration modes are very closely spaced. This means that very movements of the fingers can affect the sound significantly. The instrument is this very sensitive to expressional variations in performance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection Control Inversion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/09/04/reflection-control-inversion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection Control Inversion" /><published>2020-09-04T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-09-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/09/04/reflection-control-inversion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/09/04/reflection-control-inversion.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;reflection-49&quot;&gt;Reflection 4/9&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback instrument (contact mike, transducer, resonating plate, feedback control software) can be controlled by physically manipulating the plate. Similar to most musical instruments, we manipulate the physical object to produce different audible effects, different pitches and so on. The big difference here is that we start with what the environment (instrument system) give us as the base resonance, and then we remove (dampen) those frequencies we do not want, and then another resonance appears. It is appears somewhat zen-like: you can not decide, you can not want, but you can adapt to what is there. It is an inversion of performance in that the performer removes what they do not want, rather than producing those things they want. It is also a close symbiosis between player and instrument, between listening and actuating, …&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Reflection 4/9 The feedback instrument (contact mike, transducer, resonating plate, feedback control software) can be controlled by physically manipulating the plate. Similar to most musical instruments, we manipulate the physical object to produce different audible effects, different pitches and so on. The big difference here is that we start with what the environment (instrument system) give us as the base resonance, and then we remove (dampen) those frequencies we do not want, and then another resonance appears. It is appears somewhat zen-like: you can not decide, you can not want, but you can adapt to what is there. It is an inversion of performance in that the performer removes what they do not want, rather than producing those things they want. It is also a close symbiosis between player and instrument, between listening and actuating, …</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Workshop</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/25/workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Workshop" /><published>2020-08-25T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/25/workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/25/workshop.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;testing-a-selection-of-materials-in-the-material-technology-lab-at-ntnu&quot;&gt;Testing a selection of materials in the material technology lab at NTNU&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes:
Tested resonance and feedback on a variety of different materials. Starting with wide approach: aluminum, steel, brass, glass, polymers with different stiffness, density and porosity. Metals and glass have a rich spectrum, but are somewhat hard to control in the upper frequency range. Wood have pleasant and rich resonances, but it also varies a lot between samples. For repeatability and predictability in treatments/modifications, it would be better to have materials of a more uniform nature. Some polymers exhibit similar characteristics, like polycarbonate and bakelite. Softer plastics like PVC and acrylic glass exhibit much more “dead” response and as such not so attractive for resonance and feedback.
We made two polycarbonate samples with identical geometry, adding perforations on one of these, as to investigate the effect of perforations on the harmonic spectrum of the objects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Testing a selection of materials in the material technology lab at NTNU Notes: Tested resonance and feedback on a variety of different materials. Starting with wide approach: aluminum, steel, brass, glass, polymers with different stiffness, density and porosity. Metals and glass have a rich spectrum, but are somewhat hard to control in the upper frequency range. Wood have pleasant and rich resonances, but it also varies a lot between samples. For repeatability and predictability in treatments/modifications, it would be better to have materials of a more uniform nature. Some polymers exhibit similar characteristics, like polycarbonate and bakelite. Softer plastics like PVC and acrylic glass exhibit much more “dead” response and as such not so attractive for resonance and feedback. We made two polycarbonate samples with identical geometry, adding perforations on one of these, as to investigate the effect of perforations on the harmonic spectrum of the objects.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Antagelse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/antagelse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antagelse" /><published>2020-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/antagelse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/antagelse.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;antagelse-128&quot;&gt;Antagelse 12/8&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For måling av integritet i ukjent objekt: anta at vi kan finne moder for resonans i objektet. Ideelt sett er disse «rene», dvs i samsvar med harmoniske deltoner. Man må justere for latency i feedback loop. F.eks. hvis man har en latency på 2 millisec, og måler en resonansfrekvens på 83Hz (=12ms roundtrip), så er objektets egenresonans 100Hz (=10ms roundtrip). Man vil da forvente å kunne finne en mode på 200Hz (=5ms roundtrip), men denne ligger nå på 142Hz (7ms, dvs 5+2ms). Man vil antageligvis måtte måle mange moder og sammenholde med antatt overtonemønster for å kunne si om disse stemmer overens. For å si noe om objektets integritet kan man beregne lydens hastighet i objektet og dermed finne forventet grunntone (round trip tid), og overtoner/moder justert for latency. Ved å eksitere forskjellige moder vil man kunne frambringe disse resonansene. Hvis ikke, er det mulig at objektet ikke er intakt i hele sin lengde, men har strukturelle svakheter. De overtoner man faktisk finner til stede som resonansfrekvenser vil peke på mulige lengder objektet kan ha, og man kan derfor si noe om posisjon for mulige strukturelle svakheter. Disse antatte posisjonene kan danne grunnlag for videre undersøkelser med andre metoder og verktøy.
Det er introduksjonen av latency (ekstra forsinkelsesledd) i feedback-loopen som gjør at vi kan anta noe om objektets lengde. Uten ekstra forsinkelse skal overtonene sammenfalle med harmoniske (eller andre forventede) mønster. Disse vil forskyves på grunn av latency, og vi har derfor 2 peilepunkter: forventet overtonemønster, og forskjøvet overtonemønster. Hvis ikke disse to stemmer overens er det sannsynlig at objektets lengde ikke er den vi tror (dvs at det finnes strukturelle svakheter som påvirker refleksjonene). Det kan være usikkerheter forbundet med beregning av faktisk lengde ut fra påviste resonanser i de tilfeller det ikke stemmer med beregninger. Dette er fordi man da må prøve og feile inntil man finner et samsvar mellom påviste resonansmønster og mulig lengde på objekt.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Antagelse 12/8 For måling av integritet i ukjent objekt: anta at vi kan finne moder for resonans i objektet. Ideelt sett er disse «rene», dvs i samsvar med harmoniske deltoner. Man må justere for latency i feedback loop. F.eks. hvis man har en latency på 2 millisec, og måler en resonansfrekvens på 83Hz (=12ms roundtrip), så er objektets egenresonans 100Hz (=10ms roundtrip). Man vil da forvente å kunne finne en mode på 200Hz (=5ms roundtrip), men denne ligger nå på 142Hz (7ms, dvs 5+2ms). Man vil antageligvis måtte måle mange moder og sammenholde med antatt overtonemønster for å kunne si om disse stemmer overens. For å si noe om objektets integritet kan man beregne lydens hastighet i objektet og dermed finne forventet grunntone (round trip tid), og overtoner/moder justert for latency. Ved å eksitere forskjellige moder vil man kunne frambringe disse resonansene. Hvis ikke, er det mulig at objektet ikke er intakt i hele sin lengde, men har strukturelle svakheter. De overtoner man faktisk finner til stede som resonansfrekvenser vil peke på mulige lengder objektet kan ha, og man kan derfor si noe om posisjon for mulige strukturelle svakheter. Disse antatte posisjonene kan danne grunnlag for videre undersøkelser med andre metoder og verktøy. Det er introduksjonen av latency (ekstra forsinkelsesledd) i feedback-loopen som gjør at vi kan anta noe om objektets lengde. Uten ekstra forsinkelse skal overtonene sammenfalle med harmoniske (eller andre forventede) mønster. Disse vil forskyves på grunn av latency, og vi har derfor 2 peilepunkter: forventet overtonemønster, og forskjøvet overtonemønster. Hvis ikke disse to stemmer overens er det sannsynlig at objektets lengde ikke er den vi tror (dvs at det finnes strukturelle svakheter som påvirker refleksjonene). Det kan være usikkerheter forbundet med beregning av faktisk lengde ut fra påviste resonanser i de tilfeller det ikke stemmer med beregninger. Dette er fordi man da må prøve og feile inntil man finner et samsvar mellom påviste resonansmønster og mulig lengde på objekt.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Meeting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/project-meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Meeting" /><published>2020-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/project-meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/project-meeting.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes-from-project-meeting-128&quot;&gt;Notes from project meeting 12/8&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intro, Øyvind, instrument making process and physical models
Alex, on COS band and performances, electric shoe, 3D printing in SF, objects, instruments as art pieces. Shoe as spectacle and statement in performance, not for playing regular songs.
Kaspar. NDT. Non destructive testing. Vibration testing. Audio and ultrasonic. Well established methods for testing.
Limitations in producing materials, but experiment with available scraps and sheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strings. Bands. Metal bands as material?
Dev circle: artistic – tech dev – instrument – performance- then back&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tour of facilities.
Carbon – stiff, light, mainly one fundamental tone
Tubes give resonant frequency longitudinal and circular waves, transversal waves on long tubes
Polymers, epoxy, fillers. Polymer has lower stiffness, and thus lower fundamental frequency for object of same size. High damping, so energy dissipates (converted to heat).
In workshop: metal plates, steel, bronze, copper, thicknesses, cut out holes, aluminum plate with picture (less density on one end of plate due to shaping process), titanium plate ? (unavailable today), steel bands very interesting and bouncy properties. Børge at the workshop very interested in sound and speakers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Notes from project meeting 12/8</summary></entry></feed>