<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-21T12:00:23+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Vibrotactile materials in artistic performance</title><subtitle>Exploring feedback and resonances in various materials, by using audio feedback techniques as the exploratory device. Utilizing these methods to create new instruments for artistic performance. The mthods also give us the opportunity to reflect upon the differences between a scientific measurement and and artistic exploration (of these materials, but supposedly the poerspective might be transferrable to other domains of study). The github site is the project bog, and might also hold sources of software made for the project.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Stardust</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/12/09/stardust.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stardust" /><published>2020-12-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/12/09/stardust</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/12/09/stardust.html">&lt;p&gt;Inspired by the exhibition &lt;a href=&quot;https://samtidskunst.no/en/event/transgression&quot;&gt;Transgression&lt;/a&gt; by Reinhold Ziegler, I wanted to see how meteorite dust would work as the powdery substance to create Cymatics patterns on the feedback plates. Reinhold generously provided me with some dust, a residue from his production process.
The powder is very characteristic, fine grained, and sticks to everything (!). From how it behaves on the magnetic transducer (the speaker/vibrator element on the plate), we can also assume that it contains some iron granules as we see some darker colored particles gather close to the transducer. Also, different size particles behave differently, and thus they gather into separate “heaps” in the cymatics patterns. Also interesting is the “volcanic” puffing activity for a few seconds around 1:26 in the video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video recorded 9. December 2020. Performer: Øyvind Brandtsegg.
&lt;a href=&quot;../../../media/meteorite_dust_2020_12_09.webm&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/meteorite_dust_2020_12_09_still.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alternate Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Inspired by the exhibition Transgression by Reinhold Ziegler, I wanted to see how meteorite dust would work as the powdery substance to create Cymatics patterns on the feedback plates. Reinhold generously provided me with some dust, a residue from his production process. The powder is very characteristic, fine grained, and sticks to everything (!). From how it behaves on the magnetic transducer (the speaker/vibrator element on the plate), we can also assume that it contains some iron granules as we see some darker colored particles gather close to the transducer. Also, different size particles behave differently, and thus they gather into separate “heaps” in the cymatics patterns. Also interesting is the “volcanic” puffing activity for a few seconds around 1:26 in the video.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flour</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/11/27/flour.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flour" /><published>2020-11-27T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/11/27/flour</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/11/27/flour.html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to see if &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cymatics&quot;&gt;Cymatics&lt;/a&gt; techniques could be used to visualize the vibrational modes of our feedback plates. One would think so… but it seems so far I just found a new immensely pleasing toy. The powder moves according to vibration and form shapes, but they seem much more complex than the typical symmetric Chladni patterns. On first impression, this seems counterintuitive to me, since the feedback circuit (sound coming into the plate from a transducer, being picked up by the piezo on my finger and run back to the plate) should basically make the plate sing on one of its basic vibrational modes. Moreover, I can sort of direct the powder to move around the plate according to how I move my finger. Nothing very precise, but we can notice a correlation…. yet to be explored more. another nice surprise was when I tried to use regular wheat flour as the powder, as it “clumps” (condense, coagulate … what do you call it when that happens to powder?) into interesting shapes. Sometimes we get small balls of four, sometimes rotating cylinders/worms.  By lucky chance I had a package of sugar/cinnamon mix in my desk drawer (for some reason…), and sprinkled that on the plate together with the flour. The different characteristics of flour/cinnamon/sugar made for some nice patterns. And my whole studio now smells nicely like cinnamon buns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video recorded 27. November 2020. Performer: Øyvind Brandtsegg.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/_8yQPSao19M&quot; title=&quot;Link Title&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/flour_full_2020_11_27_still.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alternate Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I wanted to see if Cymatics techniques could be used to visualize the vibrational modes of our feedback plates. One would think so… but it seems so far I just found a new immensely pleasing toy. The powder moves according to vibration and form shapes, but they seem much more complex than the typical symmetric Chladni patterns. On first impression, this seems counterintuitive to me, since the feedback circuit (sound coming into the plate from a transducer, being picked up by the piezo on my finger and run back to the plate) should basically make the plate sing on one of its basic vibrational modes. Moreover, I can sort of direct the powder to move around the plate according to how I move my finger. Nothing very precise, but we can notice a correlation…. yet to be explored more. another nice surprise was when I tried to use regular wheat flour as the powder, as it “clumps” (condense, coagulate … what do you call it when that happens to powder?) into interesting shapes. Sometimes we get small balls of four, sometimes rotating cylinders/worms. By lucky chance I had a package of sugar/cinnamon mix in my desk drawer (for some reason…), and sprinkled that on the plate together with the flour. The different characteristics of flour/cinnamon/sugar made for some nice patterns. And my whole studio now smells nicely like cinnamon buns.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Concrete</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/11/16/concrete.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Concrete" /><published>2020-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/11/16/concrete</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/11/16/concrete.html">&lt;p&gt;In our original project plan, we had discussed briefly the possibility of using feedback techniques to investigate larger structures and buildings. I felt the urge to do some initial tests to see if we could get this kind of feedback going with heavier materials. Testing on a small concrete slab, I had to turn up the power somewhat, but not to an extreme degree. I did not measure the exact difference, but it should be in the order of 10 dB. The first feedback resonances appeared at around 8kHz, which is kind of painful to listen to, then with regular equalizing and compression, I got more resonances at around 4kHz and 6kHz (not in harmonic relationships, even though the approximate numbers might give that impression: the exact numbers where 8381 Hz, 5630 Hz, 4714 Hz, and after moving the microphone slightly I also got one at 1240 Hz).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/Concrete_slab_2020_11_16.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Concrete slab feedback&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In our original project plan, we had discussed briefly the possibility of using feedback techniques to investigate larger structures and buildings. I felt the urge to do some initial tests to see if we could get this kind of feedback going with heavier materials. Testing on a small concrete slab, I had to turn up the power somewhat, but not to an extreme degree. I did not measure the exact difference, but it should be in the order of 10 dB. The first feedback resonances appeared at around 8kHz, which is kind of painful to listen to, then with regular equalizing and compression, I got more resonances at around 4kHz and 6kHz (not in harmonic relationships, even though the approximate numbers might give that impression: the exact numbers where 8381 Hz, 5630 Hz, 4714 Hz, and after moving the microphone slightly I also got one at 1240 Hz).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Frequency_and_phase</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/28/frequency_and_phase.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Frequency_and_phase" /><published>2020-10-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/28/frequency_and_phase</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/28/frequency_and_phase.html">&lt;p&gt;With the help of NTNU colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ntnu.no/ansatte/peter.svensson&quot;&gt;Peter Svensson&lt;/a&gt; from the Acoustics group at the Department of Electronic Systems, we analyzed the frequency and phase response of the audio system without the plate. The conclusion is … that this is complex, but we have some insights.
We can see some peaks in the frequency response, that on first sight might look to be harmonically related. On closer inspection, they are not exactly at harmonic, but close. An interesting insight I learned from Peter is also that the phase response of the system crucially determines the feedback potential. It is obvious when you know, but I must admit I had not thought of it before. So, to enable feedback to be amplified on each iteration through the signal chain we must have a phase response which is a multiple of 360 degrees in addition to a peak in the frequency response. Let’s say for example, if the phase is inverted (180 degrees), that frequency will not resonate as it effectively cancel itself out. This interestingly enough creates additional potential resonance frequencies at frequencies where we might not intuitively expect them. See the close-up plot of the frequency response, with red circles indicating frequencies that will have a phase response that is an exact multiple of 360.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/freq_plot2_closeup.png&quot; alt=&quot;Close-up of frequency plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the full frequency plot for reference:
&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/freq_plot2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Full frequency plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is a &lt;a href=&quot;../../../media/Feedbackplate.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; with further analysis from Peter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still are not sure why I can get “pitch bends” with increasing pressure in the video (no plate) from 26. October.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">With the help of NTNU colleague Peter Svensson from the Acoustics group at the Department of Electronic Systems, we analyzed the frequency and phase response of the audio system without the plate. The conclusion is … that this is complex, but we have some insights. We can see some peaks in the frequency response, that on first sight might look to be harmonically related. On closer inspection, they are not exactly at harmonic, but close. An interesting insight I learned from Peter is also that the phase response of the system crucially determines the feedback potential. It is obvious when you know, but I must admit I had not thought of it before. So, to enable feedback to be amplified on each iteration through the signal chain we must have a phase response which is a multiple of 360 degrees in addition to a peak in the frequency response. Let’s say for example, if the phase is inverted (180 degrees), that frequency will not resonate as it effectively cancel itself out. This interestingly enough creates additional potential resonance frequencies at frequencies where we might not intuitively expect them. See the close-up plot of the frequency response, with red circles indicating frequencies that will have a phase response that is an exact multiple of 360.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">No Plate</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/26/no-plate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Plate" /><published>2020-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/26/no-plate</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/26/no-plate.html">&lt;p&gt;Investigating the resonance potential of the audio processing circuit without the plate. The software on screen shows the strongest frequency components in the audio signal. Notice the different feedback frequencies that can be produced by varying the pressure of the finger towards the transducer. It seems intuitive that we can produce harmonic partials with integer relationships, but how can we explain the glissando?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video recorded 26. October 2020. Performer: Øyvind Brandtsegg.
&lt;a href=&quot;../../../media/no_plate_2020_10_26.webm&quot; title=&quot;Link Title&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/no_plate_2020_10_26_still.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alternate Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Investigating the resonance potential of the audio processing circuit without the plate. The software on screen shows the strongest frequency components in the audio signal. Notice the different feedback frequencies that can be produced by varying the pressure of the finger towards the transducer. It seems intuitive that we can produce harmonic partials with integer relationships, but how can we explain the glissando?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Demovideo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/16/demovideo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Demovideo" /><published>2020-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/16/demovideo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/16/demovideo.html">&lt;p&gt;A short demo video made in the office. A 30x30cm polycarbonate plate, transducer mounted somewhat offcenter. Piezo microphone attached to finger. The sound of the microphone is routed back to the transducer, and the feedback circuit is closed when the finger touches the plate. The plate has many vibrational modes, each of which has a resonance potential at a specific frequency. By moving the finger to different positions on the plate, different vibrational modes can be activated, and the mode frequency contributes to the resonance of the feedback loop. By touching the plate with a second finger (other than the one with the microphone attached), I can dampen selected vibrational modes, and thus suppress feedback on that frequency. This allows other resonance potentials to rise and become the most prominent, thereby changing the pitch of the sound we hear. In certain conditions, several vibrational modes can become approximately equal in strength, and then we will hear several frequencies at the same time. Some of the vibration modes are very closely spaced. This means that very movements of the fingers can affect the sound significantly. The instrument is this very sensitive to expressional variations in performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video recorded 15. October 2020. Performer: Øyvind Brandtsegg.
&lt;a href=&quot;../../../media/materials_feed_demo_2020_10_14.webm&quot; title=&quot;Link Title&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/materials_demo_video_still.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alternate Text&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A short demo video made in the office. A 30x30cm polycarbonate plate, transducer mounted somewhat offcenter. Piezo microphone attached to finger. The sound of the microphone is routed back to the transducer, and the feedback circuit is closed when the finger touches the plate. The plate has many vibrational modes, each of which has a resonance potential at a specific frequency. By moving the finger to different positions on the plate, different vibrational modes can be activated, and the mode frequency contributes to the resonance of the feedback loop. By touching the plate with a second finger (other than the one with the microphone attached), I can dampen selected vibrational modes, and thus suppress feedback on that frequency. This allows other resonance potentials to rise and become the most prominent, thereby changing the pitch of the sound we hear. In certain conditions, several vibrational modes can become approximately equal in strength, and then we will hear several frequencies at the same time. Some of the vibration modes are very closely spaced. This means that very movements of the fingers can affect the sound significantly. The instrument is this very sensitive to expressional variations in performance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflection Substantiation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/01/reflection-substantiation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection Substantiation" /><published>2020-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/01/reflection-substantiation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/10/01/reflection-substantiation.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;reflection-110&quot;&gt;Reflection 1/10&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have done some more experiments on what we thought would be highly predictable resonating objects and it seems some lessons are learned. For these experiments, we mounted the microphone on a finger so that we could probe different parts of the object. The exciter transducer was mounted stationary on the object. Previously, we had been doing some tests with beams of polycarbonate, thinking that the beams would ne highly predictable. Then again, in our experience, they seemed to have less interesting properties than plates (as expected, with vibration nodes in just one dimension), but also still being somewhat unpredictable. For this reason we turned to resonating strings in a music instrument, an object that we thought we would have a clear understanding of. The harmonics of a string are well described, for an introduction, see: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_harmonic&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_harmonic&lt;/a&gt;.
We did, however encounter some interesting deviations from what we could expect from an ideal string. Some of the partials was easily accessible, although not on the exact physical position where one might initially expect. Oftentimes a slight offset in position was needed with respect to the mathematical subdivision, although the activation point was not symmetrical around the mathematical subdivision. Other partials was not accessible, or they were replaced by higher partials within the same ratio (1/3 being replaced by 1/6). Resonances corresponding to the remaining string length did also occur, as in line 6) of the illustration. Finally, we also experienced other resonance potentials not intuitively related to the position on the string where we put the microphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/Stringmodes.png&quot; alt=&quot;String modes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dividing a string by a light touch of the finger, as line in 3) of the illustration, forces the string to vibrate on the corresponding harmonic partial. All rational subdivisions of the string (1/2, 1/3, 1/4, 3/4, etc) produce harmonic partials corresponding to the denominator of the subdivision. (Ilustration: Wikipedia)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/Guitar_resonator.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Guitar resonator&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;The experiment setup with transducer (front), finger dividing the string at the halfway point, and a contact microphone on the finger. (Photo: ØB)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As one might reasonably object&lt;/strong&gt;, the experimental setup is not simply the ideal string. It also includes significant contributions from the resonating body of the guitar, the filtering of vibrations going through the finger, the frequency response of the microphone and the transducer, and finally also a the timing latency and frequency response of the audio system between microphone and transducer. In our case, we run the sound through a computer, in order to be able to do arbitrary complex processing of the signal ad hoc as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../media/Feedback_flowchart_2020_09.png&quot; alt=&quot;Signal flow&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;em&gt;Signal flow of the feedback experiment with acoustic guitar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With an intuitive&lt;/strong&gt; analysis of the system, we could assume to find resonance potential with contributions from all parts of the signal chain. Also, the total frequency response (resonance potential) could be analyzed as a convolution of the frequency response of all contributing components. This would mean that any resonance potential in common between the contribution components would become exponentially amplified, compared to resonances that appear in one of the components only. The feedback circuit enables any resonance to be amplified, and since it is a closed loop, the sound passes repeatedly through the resonating component. When resonance occurs, it is quickly amplified, and thus also will cancel out any competing resonant frequencies. This means that the system can be described as a chaotic system, where the behavior is deterministic but extremely sensitive to initial conditions. For us, this means that a weakly resonating partial in the string, if it correlates with a resonant frequency somewhere else in the system, might make the feedback “catch on” and then overpower other resonating frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One could do a thorough technical analysis of the system&lt;/strong&gt;, to take an impulse response of all components, do the convolution and then predict the sum of potential resonances. Doing this for all possible microphone positions would be a substantial effort, and the microphone positions would have to be discretized somehow to arrive at a finite number of observations to make. Imagining for a moment that we would do such an analysis, we envision that the outcome would be a table of resonant frequencies related to microphone positions. This could be very useful, but also a data source with considerable scope for error due to the system’s sensitivity to initial conditions. Minor inaccuracies in microphone position enables the feedback to catch on to a competing (close by) resonance potential. Once the feedback catches on, this resonance will usually be amplified and overpower other competing resonances. For this reason, such an analysis might be of limited value, and could also be directly misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An artistic exploration&lt;/strong&gt; of the resonance potential is useful in this case, simply because the performer investigating the properties of the object will automatically adjust to the systems sensitivity to initial conditions and thus be able to explore the potential more fully and truthfully. This is a bold claim, and we will try to substantiate it: A music instrument performer is trained to adapt to the instrument, as a means to bring out the desired sounds from it. This adaptive exploration mode is helpful when exploring an object which is acutely sensitive to initial conditions. During free exploration of an instrument, when a sound (that the performer finds interesting) emanates from the instrument, they will attempt to reproduce the sound repeatedly in order to gain control of the instrument. This is an act of building a repertoire of instrumental actions that again construes a sound language from the potential of the instrument. Being able to repeatedly reproduce these linguistic “syllables” is part of the process of gaining expressive control of the instrument. The adaptive exploration mode allows minute adjustments to the performance gestures (e.g. microphone placement in our case), which again significantly affects which resonances will be activated. It is thus possible to iteratively explore a large number of closely spaced and competing resonances in a predictable manner. However, the resulting “data set” is less easily compressed into a table of positions and frequencies, since it also includes performer skill and intuition as a significant part of the knowledge achieved though the experiment. Performer skill and intuition are easily recognized as constituent parts of the knowledge, but are less easily quantified numerically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One could claim&lt;/strong&gt; that this is a strong point for artistic exploration per se, as the artistic process includes “attractors” in the potential of the material being investigated. This allows for a much more nuanced exploration of those areas, with an adaptive resolution of measurement inherent in the process. In the case of feedback exploration, the adaptive microphone positioning done by the performer can reveal object properties invisible (or unattainable) to a quantized and more scientific approach.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Reflection 1/10 We have done some more experiments on what we thought would be highly predictable resonating objects and it seems some lessons are learned. For these experiments, we mounted the microphone on a finger so that we could probe different parts of the object. The exciter transducer was mounted stationary on the object. Previously, we had been doing some tests with beams of polycarbonate, thinking that the beams would ne highly predictable. Then again, in our experience, they seemed to have less interesting properties than plates (as expected, with vibration nodes in just one dimension), but also still being somewhat unpredictable. For this reason we turned to resonating strings in a music instrument, an object that we thought we would have a clear understanding of. The harmonics of a string are well described, for an introduction, see: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_harmonic. We did, however encounter some interesting deviations from what we could expect from an ideal string. Some of the partials was easily accessible, although not on the exact physical position where one might initially expect. Oftentimes a slight offset in position was needed with respect to the mathematical subdivision, although the activation point was not symmetrical around the mathematical subdivision. Other partials was not accessible, or they were replaced by higher partials within the same ratio (1/3 being replaced by 1/6). Resonances corresponding to the remaining string length did also occur, as in line 6) of the illustration. Finally, we also experienced other resonance potentials not intuitively related to the position on the string where we put the microphone.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Workshop</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/25/workshop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Workshop" /><published>2020-08-25T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/25/workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/25/workshop.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;testing-a-selection-of-materials-in-the-material-technology-lab-at-ntnu&quot;&gt;Testing a selection of materials in the material technology lab at NTNU&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes:
Tested resonance and feedback on a variety of different materials. Starting with wide approach: aluminum, steel, brass, glass, polymers with different stiffness, density and porosity. Metals and glass have a rich spectrum, but are somewhat hard to control in the upper frequency range. Wood have pleasant and rich resonances, but it also varies a lot between samples. For repeatability and predictability in treatments/modifications, it would be better to have materials of a more uniform nature. Some polymers exhibit similar characteristics, like polycarbonate and bakelite. Softer plastics like PVC and acrylic glass exhibit much more “dead” response and as such not so attractive for resonance and feedback.
We made two polycarbonate samples with identical geometry, adding perforations on one of these, as to investigate the effect of perforations on the harmonic spectrum of the objects.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Testing a selection of materials in the material technology lab at NTNU Notes: Tested resonance and feedback on a variety of different materials. Starting with wide approach: aluminum, steel, brass, glass, polymers with different stiffness, density and porosity. Metals and glass have a rich spectrum, but are somewhat hard to control in the upper frequency range. Wood have pleasant and rich resonances, but it also varies a lot between samples. For repeatability and predictability in treatments/modifications, it would be better to have materials of a more uniform nature. Some polymers exhibit similar characteristics, like polycarbonate and bakelite. Softer plastics like PVC and acrylic glass exhibit much more “dead” response and as such not so attractive for resonance and feedback. We made two polycarbonate samples with identical geometry, adding perforations on one of these, as to investigate the effect of perforations on the harmonic spectrum of the objects.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Antagelse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/antagelse.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antagelse" /><published>2020-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/antagelse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/antagelse.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;antagelse-128&quot;&gt;Antagelse 12/8&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For måling av integritet i ukjent objekt: anta at vi kan finne moder for resonans i objektet. Ideelt sett er disse «rene», dvs i samsvar med harmoniske deltoner. Man må justere for latency i feedback loop. F.eks. hvis man har en latency på 2 millisec, og måler en resonansfrekvens på 83Hz (=12ms roundtrip), så er objektets egenresonans 100Hz (=10ms roundtrip). Man vil da forvente å kunne finne en mode på 200Hz (=5ms roundtrip), men denne ligger nå på 142Hz (7ms, dvs 5+2ms). Man vil antageligvis måtte måle mange moder og sammenholde med antatt overtonemønster for å kunne si om disse stemmer overens. For å si noe om objektets integritet kan man beregne lydens hastighet i objektet og dermed finne forventet grunntone (round trip tid), og overtoner/moder justert for latency. Ved å eksitere forskjellige moder vil man kunne frambringe disse resonansene. Hvis ikke, er det mulig at objektet ikke er intakt i hele sin lengde, men har strukturelle svakheter. De overtoner man faktisk finner til stede som resonansfrekvenser vil peke på mulige lengder objektet kan ha, og man kan derfor si noe om posisjon for mulige strukturelle svakheter. Disse antatte posisjonene kan danne grunnlag for videre undersøkelser med andre metoder og verktøy.
Det er introduksjonen av latency (ekstra forsinkelsesledd) i feedback-loopen som gjør at vi kan anta noe om objektets lengde. Uten ekstra forsinkelse skal overtonene sammenfalle med harmoniske (eller andre forventede) mønster. Disse vil forskyves på grunn av latency, og vi har derfor 2 peilepunkter: forventet overtonemønster, og forskjøvet overtonemønster. Hvis ikke disse to stemmer overens er det sannsynlig at objektets lengde ikke er den vi tror (dvs at det finnes strukturelle svakheter som påvirker refleksjonene). Det kan være usikkerheter forbundet med beregning av faktisk lengde ut fra påviste resonanser i de tilfeller det ikke stemmer med beregninger. Dette er fordi man da må prøve og feile inntil man finner et samsvar mellom påviste resonansmønster og mulig lengde på objekt.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Antagelse 12/8 For måling av integritet i ukjent objekt: anta at vi kan finne moder for resonans i objektet. Ideelt sett er disse «rene», dvs i samsvar med harmoniske deltoner. Man må justere for latency i feedback loop. F.eks. hvis man har en latency på 2 millisec, og måler en resonansfrekvens på 83Hz (=12ms roundtrip), så er objektets egenresonans 100Hz (=10ms roundtrip). Man vil da forvente å kunne finne en mode på 200Hz (=5ms roundtrip), men denne ligger nå på 142Hz (7ms, dvs 5+2ms). Man vil antageligvis måtte måle mange moder og sammenholde med antatt overtonemønster for å kunne si om disse stemmer overens. For å si noe om objektets integritet kan man beregne lydens hastighet i objektet og dermed finne forventet grunntone (round trip tid), og overtoner/moder justert for latency. Ved å eksitere forskjellige moder vil man kunne frambringe disse resonansene. Hvis ikke, er det mulig at objektet ikke er intakt i hele sin lengde, men har strukturelle svakheter. De overtoner man faktisk finner til stede som resonansfrekvenser vil peke på mulige lengder objektet kan ha, og man kan derfor si noe om posisjon for mulige strukturelle svakheter. Disse antatte posisjonene kan danne grunnlag for videre undersøkelser med andre metoder og verktøy. Det er introduksjonen av latency (ekstra forsinkelsesledd) i feedback-loopen som gjør at vi kan anta noe om objektets lengde. Uten ekstra forsinkelse skal overtonene sammenfalle med harmoniske (eller andre forventede) mønster. Disse vil forskyves på grunn av latency, og vi har derfor 2 peilepunkter: forventet overtonemønster, og forskjøvet overtonemønster. Hvis ikke disse to stemmer overens er det sannsynlig at objektets lengde ikke er den vi tror (dvs at det finnes strukturelle svakheter som påvirker refleksjonene). Det kan være usikkerheter forbundet med beregning av faktisk lengde ut fra påviste resonanser i de tilfeller det ikke stemmer med beregninger. Dette er fordi man da må prøve og feile inntil man finner et samsvar mellom påviste resonansmønster og mulig lengde på objekt.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project Meeting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/project-meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project Meeting" /><published>2020-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-08-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/project-meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vibrotactile/2020/08/12/project-meeting.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes-from-project-meeting-128&quot;&gt;Notes from project meeting 12/8&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intro, Øyvind, instrument making process and physical models
Alex, on COS band and performances, electric shoe, 3D printing in SF, objects, instruments as art pieces. Shoe as spectacle and statement in performance, not for playing regular songs.
Kaspar. NDT. Non destructive testing. Vibration testing. Audio and ultrasonic. Well established methods for testing.
Limitations in producing materials, but experiment with available scraps and sheets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strings. Bands. Metal bands as material?
Dev circle: artistic – tech dev – instrument – performance- then back&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tour of facilities.
Carbon – stiff, light, mainly one fundamental tone
Tubes give resonant frequency longitudinal and circular waves, transversal waves on long tubes
Polymers, epoxy, fillers. Polymer has lower stiffness, and thus lower fundamental frequency for object of same size. High damping, so energy dissipates (converted to heat).
In workshop: metal plates, steel, bronze, copper, thicknesses, cut out holes, aluminum plate with picture (less density on one end of plate due to shaping process), titanium plate ? (unavailable today), steel bands very interesting and bouncy properties. Børge at the workshop very interested in sound and speakers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Notes from project meeting 12/8</summary></entry></feed>